A Guide to the Project Files, University of Virginia Library Special Collections Building, 1938-2001 (bulk 1971-2001)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Project Files, University of Virginia Library Special Collections Building 1938-2001 (bulk 1971-2001)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-12/1/7.991
This collection consists of ca. 5000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was an archival transfer from Edmund Berkeley, January 26, 1999.
Scope and Content
Records (ca. 5000 items) accumulated by Edmund Berkeley, Jr., de facto coordinator of the University of Virginia's interest in and efforts to construct a special collections library building. The records contain justification statements including one by consultant Ellsworth Mason, recommendations, fund raising materials, architect's presentation materials, correspondence, and files on special collections buildings elsewhere dating from 1938, equipment, preliminary blueprints, site plans, and a study on the feasibility of a Special Collections wing on Alderman Library. With them are the files of former University Librarian, Ray W. Frantz, Jr. regarding the project.
Of interest are photographs of Governor James S. Gilmore, III's trip to Alderman Library to discuss the release of state funds for the Mary and David Harrison Institute for American History, Literature, and Culture and Albert H. Small Special Collections Library building. Gilmore is photographed with University President John Casteen, University Librarian Karin Wittenborg, and Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer Leonard Sandridge.
Contents List
- Architects - Cooper Lecky Architects, PC 1990 (Box 1)
- Architects - Hartman Cox Architects 1976 (Box 1)
- Architects - Hartman Cox Architects 1990 (Box 1)
- Architects - Information 1993 (Box 1)
- Architects - Michael Dennis & Associates 1991 (Box 1)
- Architects - Mitchell/Matthews & Associates (1 volume) 1995 (Box 1)
- Architects - Mitchell/Matthews & Associates - Draft (1 volume) 1995 (Box 1)
- Architects - Shepley Bulfinch Richardson and Abbott 1991 (Box 1)
- Atmospheric Control 1992-1994 (Box 1)
- Background Reading 1953-1970 (Box 1)
- Board of Visitors - Notes for Presentation 1992 (Box 1)
- Building Committee 1991 (Box 2)
- Building Committee 1992 (Box 2)
- Building Program 1991-1993 (Box 2)
- Building Program 1994-1996 (Box 2)
- Building Program 1997 (Box 2)
- Building Program - Mitchell/Matthews 1995 (Box 2)
- Capital Budget Request Revision 1994 (Box 2)
- Compact Shelving 1996 (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1980-1992 (Box 3)
- Fire Detection, etc. 1960-1976 (Box 3)
- "The First Mark of Distinction" 1973 (Box 3)
- Formulas and Measurements 1977-1998 (Box 3)
- Fumigation Equipment 1973-1990 (Box 3)
- Fundraising - Correspondence 1973-1990 (Box 3)
- Fundraising Materials 1982-1991 (Box 3)
- Guidance for Building Committee 1993-1998 (Box 3)
- Halon - Fire Extinguisher ca. 1975, n.d. (Box 3)
- Justification Statement for Special Collections - Drafts 1974-1983 Jun (Box 3)
- Justification Statement for Special Collections - Drafts 1983 Jul-1984 (Box 4)
- Justification Statement for Special Collections - Ellsworth Mason - Consultant 1990-1995 (Box 4)
- Library Visitation Trip Report 1974 (Box 4)
- Library Expansion Building Committee 1990-1991 (Box 4)
- Lighting n.d. (Box 4)
- New Building Program - Draft n.d. (Box 4)
- New Building Program - Notes 1971-1973 (Box 4)
- Photographs of Governor James S. Gilmore, III at the University of Virginia 2001 (Box 4)
- Pre-Planning Study - Special Collections Library n.d. (Box 4)
- "Preliminary Recommendations" 1973 (Box 4)
- "Preliminary Recommendations for a Building" 1973 (Box 4)
- Security Systems n.d. (Box 4)
- Site Plan Studies [1974?] (Box 4)
- Siting Criteria n.d. (Box 4)
- Special Collections - Building or Wing 1989-1990 (Box 4)
- Special Collections Library 1992 Jan-Aug (Box 4)
- Special Collections Library 1992 Sep-Dec (Box 5)
- Special Collections Library 1993-1998 (Box 5)
- Special Collections Library - Designs 1983-1995 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings -Beinecke, Yale University 1960-1964 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings -Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan 1984 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Cornell n.d. (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - General ca. 1947-1982 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Houghton Library 1943 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Illinois Archives 1938 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Pennsylvania 1949 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Reuther - Wayne State 1975 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Spencer Library, University of Kansas 1979 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Tennessee State Library n.d. (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Toronto 1965 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Vermont Archives 1948 (Box 5)
- Special Collections - Other Buildings - Washington & Lee n.d. (Box 5)
- Special Collections Wing Program 1990-1991 (Box 5)
- Special Collections Wing - Study (1 of 2) 1991 (Box 6)
- Special Collections Wing - Study (2 of 2) 1991 (Box 6)
- Special Collections - Wing 1990-1991 (Box 6)
- Stettinius Room 1984 (Box 6)